Guide to the William Clark Grasty Papers, 1788-1906 and undated (bulk 1800-1869)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
William Clark Grasty papers 1788-1906 and undated (bulk 1800-1869)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Grasty, William Clark, b. ca. 1800
10.9 Linear Feet 8,175 Items
General merchant, Pittsylvania Co., Va.
Correspondence, account books, daybooks, fee books, invoices, ledgers, memoranda books, records of sales, inventories, and letterpress copybooks, chiefly 1800-1869, of three generations of general merchants of Pittsylvania Co., Va. Business interests included a general store, a tavern, a blacksmith shop, a simplified type of banking, and the keeping of a post office. Large amounts of tobacco were bought and sold before the Civil War. Post-war records indicate a large volume of trade in Peruvian guano and commercial fertilizers. Partners in the firm included Philip L. Grasty and other members of the Grasty family, John F. Rison and Samuel Pannill. Includes letters (1849-1867) of John S. Grasty, a Presbyterian minister, referring to North Carolina agriculture, slave hiring, Unionist sympathy among the Dutch population of Botetourt Co., Va., and the devastation of Fincastle, Va., during the war.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Clark Grasty Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1934-1937.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, account books, daybooks, fee books, invoices, ledgers, memoranda books, records of sales, inventories, and letterpress copybooks, chiefly 1800-1869, of three generations of general merchants of Pittsylvania Co., Va. Business interests included a general store, a tavern, a blacksmith shop, a simplified type of banking, and the keeping of a post office. Large amounts of tobacco were bought and sold before the Civil War. Post-war records indicate a large volume of trade in Peruvian guano and commercial fertilizers. Partners in the firm included Philip L. Grasty and other members of the Grasty family, John F. Rison and Samuel Pannill. Includes letters (1849-1867) of John S. Grasty, a Presbyterian minister, referring to North Carolina agriculture, slave hiring, Unionist sympathy among the Dutch population of Botetourt Co., Va., and the devastation of Fincastle, Va., during the war.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Agriculture -- Virginia
Banks and banking -- Virginia
Blacksmithing -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County
Dutch Americans -- Virginia -- Political activity
Fertilizer industry -- Virginia
Guano
Taverns (Inns) -- Virginia
Merchants -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County
Postal service -- Virginia -- Pittsylvania County
Presbyterian Church -- Clergy
Presbyterian Church -- Virginia
Slavery -- Virginia
Tobacco -- Marketing-- Virginia
Pittsylvania County (Va.) -- Commerce
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Destruction and pillage
Virginia -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents of Collection
- Papers Series, 1788-1906 and undated (bulk 1800-1869), (35 boxes)
  - 1788-1813 (Box 1)
  - 1814-1822 (Box 2)
  - 1823-1824 (Box 3)
  - 1825-1826 (Box 4)
  - 1827-1836 (Box 5)
  - 1837-1839 (Box 6)
  - 1840-1842 (Box 7)
  - 1843-1844 (Box 8)
  - 1845-1847 (Box 9)
  - 1848-1851 (Box 10)
  - 1852-1856 (Box 11)
  - 1857 (Box 12)
  - 1858 Jan.-June (Box 13)
  - 1858 July-Dec. (Box 14)
  - 1859 Jan.-Apr. (Box 15)
  - 1859 May-Dec. (Box 16)
  - 1860 Jan.-Mar. (Box 17)
  - 1860 Apr.-Sept. (Box 18)
  - 1860 Oct.-1861 Mar. (Box 19)
  - 1861 Apr.-Aug. (Box 20)
  - 1861 Sept.-1862 Feb. (Box 21)
  - 1862 Mar.-Aug. (Box 22)
  - 1862 Sept.-1863 Apr. (Box 23)
  - 1863 May-Dec. (Box 24)
  - 1864 Jan.-Sept. (Box 25)
  - 1864 Oct.-1865 July (Box 26)
  - 1865 Aug.-1866 Apr. (Box 27)
  - 1866 May-1867 June (Box 28)
  - 1867 July-Dec. (Box 29)
  - 1868 Jan.-July (Box 30)
  - 1868 Aug.-1869 June (Box 31)
  - 1870-1876 and undated (Box 32)
  - 1870-1906 and undated (Box 33)
  - undated (Box 34-35)
- Volumes Series, 1788-1868, (9 boxes)
  - Grasty, Jane W., memorandum book, 1828 (Box 36)
  - Grasty, Philip L.
    - Fee book, 1788
    - Account books, 1806-1807
    - Blotters
      - 1818-1822
      - 1824-1868 (Box 37)
    - Day books
      - 1804-1805
      - 1805-1818 (Box 38)
      - 1819-1823 (Box 39)
      - 1823-1826 (Box 40)
      - 1826-1827 (Box 41)
    - Index book
    - Invoice book, 1820
    - Ledger, 1814-1815
    - Memorandum book
      - 1800-1803
      - 1821-1826 (Box 42)
    - Sales book and cash book, 1827-1828
    - Shop books, 1816-1822
    - Tobacco book, 1800-1809
  - Grasty, Philip L. and Samuel Pannill
    - Account book, 1800-1806
    - Day book, 1801-1819 (Box 43)
    - Miscellaneous printed material, 1859-1868
    - Inventory, 1801-1806 (Box 44)
    - Invoice book, 1799-1805
  - Grasty, William Clark
    - Cash book, 1840-1842
    - Day book, 1838-1839
    - Memorandum books, 1837-1844
    - Miscellaneous account books, 1838-1859
  - Rison, John F., account book, 1868
  - Other account books, 1849-1867
- Other Manuscript Volumes
  - L:1469; L:1537; L:1543-1545; L:1547; L:1552; L:1556; L:1559; L:1563; L:1574, M:1566; M:1575; M:3465. For locations of these volumes, please consult with a reference archivist.